Guide to the John Taylor Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Taylor correspondence
1803-1861
OSB MSS 42
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists of letters addressed to Taylor by various correspondents, including Richard Ayton, Octavius Gilchrist, Alexander Haden and Harvey Marriott. Most concern publishing business or personal news; several discuss currency policy, an issue of great interest to Taylor.
Taylor, John, 1781-1864
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JOHN TAYLOR, 1781-1864
John Taylor was born in Nottinghamshire in 1781. Taylor moved to London about 1806, becoming a partner in the publishing firm Taylor & Hussey (later Taylor & Walton). Taylor published several works attributing the letters of "Junius" to Sir Philip Francis, an identification still widely accepted today, and served as editor of the London Magazine in 1821-24. Taylor's literary friends included Charles Lamb, Thomas Hood, and Samuel Coleridge.
Taylor, perhaps influenced by his brother, the banker James Taylor (1788-1863), was opposed to the currency policies of Sir Thomas Peel, and authored several books and pamphlets on the subject of currency reform, including "Currency Fallacies Refuted and Paper Money Vindicated" (London, 1833) and "The Monetary Policy of England and America" (London, 1843). His other works include "The Great Pyramid: Why Was It Built?" (London, 1859), and articles on antiquarian subjects for Macmillan's and the Gentleman's Magazine.
John Taylor did not marry. He died in Kensington on July 5, 1864.
Scope and Contents
The John Taylor Correspondence consists of letters sent to John Taylor, publisher. The collection spans the dates 1803-1861.
The majority of the letters concern publication business, particularly requests for payments and advances, and some contain personal news as well. Correspondents include the Revs. Basil and Harvey Marriott; Alexander Bunn Haden; Charles Caleb Colton; and the topographical writer Richard Ayton, whose letters date from the last year of his life and cover literary and political opinions as well as the gradual decline of his health. The letters of Octavius Gilchrist discuss progress on his edition of the poetry of Richard Corbet, as well as other literary projects.
Other correspondents, including John Knott and John and Philip Twells, share Taylor's interest in currency reform and offer news of the Currency Society.
Currency question -- Great Britain; Publishers and publishing -- Great Britain; Publishers; Ayton, Richard, 1786-1823; Colton, C. C. (Charles Caleb), 1780?-1832; Gilchrist, Octavius, 1779-1823; Marriott, Harvey, 1782-1865; Taylor, John, 1781-1864
- Correspondence, 1803-1861; Series I; 0.42' (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is alphabetically arranged by name of correspondent.
  - ALLISON, WILLIAM
    - 4 ALS to John Taylor; East Retford, 1843-59 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Accompanied by a letter to Miss White.
  - AYTON, RICHARD, 1786-1823
    - 17 ALS to Taylor and Hessey; Seaford and London, 1822-23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - COLTON, CHARLES CALEB, 1780-1832
    - 5 ALS to Taylor and Hessey; Tiverton, 1815-16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      On the publication of his writings. Accompanied by a copy of a letter from Taylor and Hessey to Colton, 1813 Dec 12.
  - DARLING, S.
    - 2 ALS to John Taylor; [v.p.], 1861, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - FALKNER, F.
    - 8 ALS to John Taylor; Camden Town and So. Carlton, 1841-49 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - FALKNER, JOHN S.
    - 3 ALS to John Taylor; South Carlton, 1848 Apr, Aug (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - FALKNER, M. B.
    - ALS to John Taylor; South Carlton, [n.y.] Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - FALKNER, ROBERT
    - ALS to John Taylor; Bath, 1828 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - GILCHRIST, OCTAVIUS GRAHAM, 1779-1823
    - 6 ALS to John Taylor; Stamford, 1803-07 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      On Gilchrist's edition of Richard Corbet's poetry and other literary enterprises.
  - HADEN, ALEXANDER BUNN, 1752-1829
    - ALS to John Taylor; Wolverhampton, 1810 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - HADEN, ALEXANDER BUNN, 1783-1863
    - 10 ALS to John Taylor; [v.p.], 1806-60 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - HADEN, FRANK W.
    - ALS to John Taylor; Chapel Ash, 1808 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - HADEN, S.
    - 2 ALS to John Taylor; Balham and Horsham (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - KING, THOMAS
    - 6 ALS to John Taylor; London, 1841-49 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - KNOTT, JOHN M.
    - 10 ALS to John Taylor; [v.p.], 1847-55 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Concerning the currency question.
  - MARRIOTT, BASIL
    - 7 ALS to John Taylor; [v.p.], 1812 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - MARRIOTT, HARVEY, 1782-1865
    - 14 ALS to John Taylor; [v.p.], 1811-61 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - MEE, J.
    - 9 ALS to John Taylor; East Retford, 1814-48 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - MEE, WILLIAM
    - ALS to John Taylor; [Retford], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, Retford, [1841 or later] (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - MOWER, ARTHUR
    - 4 ALS to John Taylor; 1 Park St., Edinburgh, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      With a fragment by George Mower on the finding of a giant skeleton.
  - SAMPSON, THEOPHILUS
    - ALS to John Taylor; Edwinstowe, 1820 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - STOAT, CHARLES
    - ALS to John Taylor; Retford, 1849 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - TALLANT, F.
    - 2 ALS to John Taylor; York St. and Worcester, 1842, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Personal and family news.
  - TALLANT, MARY
    - ALS to John Taylor; Liverpool, 1818 Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - TAYLOR, JOHN, 1781-1854
    - ALS (copy) to Philip Twells; Leonard Place, 1859 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - TWELLS, JOHN
    - 9 ALS to John Taylor; [v.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Concerning the Currency Society, death of Lord George Bentinck, etc.
  - TWELLS, PHILIP, 1809-1880
    - 3 ALS to John Taylor; Lincolns Inn, 1848-59 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Social and business notes. On p. 4 of one letter, some apparently unrelated genealogical notes in another hand.
  - WHITE, FREDERICK
    - 4 ALS to John Taylor; Retford, 1842-53 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      One letter written on p. 4 of a letter written by his son, F. White, Jr.
  - WHITE, JOHN
    - 2 ALS to John Taylor; Portsmouth and Cawsand, 1807, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - WHITE, MARY
    - 3 ALS to John Taylor; East Retford, 1860, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)